Inventory to the Jan Nowak Papers, 1942-1981
Hoover Institution Archives
Jan Nowak Papers,
1942-1981
67035
Nowak, Jan, 1913-
1 manuscript box, 14 phonorecords (1.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Clandestine radio dispatch transcripts, reports, memoranda and correspondence, relating to conditions in occupied Poland during World War II and to Polish resistance activities. Also includes sound recordings of speeches, radio broadcasts and later commentaries, relating to major events of twentieth-century Polish history. Photocopy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Location of Originals
Originals in possession of: J. Nowak.
Access Points
Poles in foreign countries.; Poland.; Poland--History--20th century.; Phonorecords.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Underground movements.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945.; Poland. Polskie Sily Zbrojne. Armia Krajowa
Biography
Captain, Polish army; underground courier between Warsaw and London, 1943-1945.
Container List
- British documents. Reports and letters issued in 1944 by the British Foreign Office, relating to Jan Nowak (Box 1., Folder 1)
- Correspondence with wartime associates, articles, and testimonies of various members of the Polish resistance movement during WWII (Folder 2)
- Personal documents. Copies of passports, passes, reference letters, identity cards, membership papers, etc. (Folder 3)
- Subject file
  - Missions. Clandestine cable and radio dispatch transcripts, reports, and correspondence relating to occupied Poland and to Jan Nowak's missions as an underground courier
    - First (1943 April 14-June 31, Warsaw-Stockholm-Warsaw) (Folder 4)
    - Second (1943 October 15-1944 July 25, Warsaw-Stockholm-Brindisi-Warsaw) (Folder 5)
    - Third (1944 October 3-1945 January 22, Warsaw-Krakow-Bern-London) (Folder 6)
  - Warsaw Uprising (Folder 7)
    - Cables describing events in Warsaw, 1944 August
    - Transcripts of radio broadcasts from the Warsaw Broadcasting Station
- Sound recordings of speeches, radio broadcasts, and later commentaries, relating to major events of 20th century Polish history (Phonorecord cabinet)
  - Sound recording of "Swiadkowie Historii," 1965 (Records 1-4)
    Use copy reference number: 67035_a_0001715
  - Sound recording of "Kawalkada Czasu" 1952-1964 (Records 5-6)
  - Sound recording of "Kawalkada Czasu" 1964-1974 (Records 7-8)
  - Duplicates of records 5-6 (Records 9-10)
  - Sound recording of "Sacrum Poloniae Millenium" (Records 11-12)
  - Duplicates of Records 7-8 (Records 13-14)